[music]
Not every day you get to meet a founder
of an entire category. We have Sam Lang
who is the founder of Otter AI. Uh how
many people have a notetaker on their
laptop, phone, and every other device.
Literally everybody in the room. He
invented the entire category actually.
Didn't exist before Otter AI. How many
people use Otter? Actually, yeah, most
most people. Okay. Well, you're very
familiar. This is the guy who brought it
to life, created it from scratch. And uh
I hear you have slides.
>> Oh, do you want to do them?
>> Just just um we can do them later. We
can ask questions first.
>> Do them later.
>> Yeah, you can you can do it that
question.
>> Okay. All right. We'll do questions
first. It's funny. I got two sets of
questions for you, Sam. One of them is
formal and then the other is fun
questions from from the crowd.
>> Which ones would you rather do, guys?
>> Let's just start with your formal
questions.
>> All right. We'll start formal. Yeah.
Then I'll uh I'll mix in the the fun
crowd questions. Um so Otter has
obviously been incredibly successful.
Why don't you give us just two minutes
on your your life journey that brought
you to founding the company and and the
the journey that's been epic actually.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Um thank you everyone
who has uh used Otter. Uh I'd love to
hear your feedback. Uh I was um while
we're on Google campus I was uh working
at the Google 20 years ago uh 2006 to
2010 I was the lead of Google map
location platform that powers the Google
mobile map. I'm sure most of you have
used
>> so uh it's great to come back here.
>> Um I left Google in 2010 to build a
mobile startup in Paloto first. Um and
after that was uh successfully acquired
uh with my co-founder Yungfu we started
Otter. Um that was 10 years ago before
AI became a household buzzword. Uh the
initial motivation was very simple. You
know I when I was uh working at Google
when I was doing startup uh I had to go
to tons of meetings uh both internal
meetings and external meetings with
customers investors. Uh I have really
bad memory. I cannot remember. So um I
was at that time Gmail and Google search
was so good right? You know, I was uh
fascinated that I could search for
anything uh in Gmail like almost 10 20
years ago, but I cannot search for
anything I heard 3 hours ago.
>> So then we said, okay, and that's a huge
opportunity. Let's uh build something
that can change that.
>> My uh my media team wanted me to let you
know that everything that you say today
and everything that I hear goes [snorts]
through Otter. So you'll probably see it
on your servers if you ever want to
stalk me. But we actually in all all of
our meetings for our companies now, we
use these plaids which
>> Oh yeah. Do you know you know these
things?
>> Yeah. So this thing, you know, will
record for a week. Uh it's not on right
now. I'm not I'm not spying on on Well,
it will go through because of this
anyway. But um but it's almost
impossible to imagine now having a
meeting. It's it's really weird because
you know if you drop an Fbclom or
whatever, it's all recorded. But at the
end of a meeting, the idea of doing a
wrap-up, a follow-up, uh, you know,
assigning tasks, it's like it's a
nightmare of follow-up. It's all AI
instantaneous right now. But when you
when you started Otter, the technology,
the transcription was marginal at best
and the AI didn't exist to to turn it
into action items. So, was the original
idea just capture audio or was it
searchable audio? What what was it? Uh
the original idea was um uh searchable
audio but uh but then it quickly
evolved. Uh as you mentioned when we
started back in 2016 although there was
uh Google voice there was Siri there was
uh Alexa but none of those models
actually were trained for long for
multi-speaker conversations. So we
tested everything worked. So we decided
to build our own speech recogition
technologies. Um so even today uh
everything you see on Otter uh all the
transcription speaker identification
which is another special technology were
all built inhouse. Uh we're not using
any third party API for that. So uh that
enable us to create highly accurate um
extremely fast um uh trans both
transcription and speaker uh recognition
which is actually super critical. uh
today if you uh I don't think if you use
a Google meet or zoom uh if there are
multiple people in the same room I don't
think they can separate them and
identify who is speaking
>> yeah the the attribution is critically
important and if somebody in a meeting
says yeah I'll do that
>> it's pretty important to know which
person that was and it's still pretty
pretty inaccurate I think so it's still
part of the original vision was to do
the uh the attribution to the right
speaker
>> absolutely absolutely so we've been
working on that uh for 10 years now. Um
there's um still a lot more to do.
>> And so then you know mid company cycle
AI GPT2 then three then four now five
now Astro 6. I mean the the change of
what you can do with all that
information has been astronomical. So
you must have modified the original
vision what three four five times by
now.
>> Yeah it has been evolving. um you know
but you know we we built the the m
notetaker we built this space uh we're
still you know uh rapidly growing
although there are a lot of copy cast
now there um uh Google embedded uh some
transcription and summary zoom embedded
that although we actually the zoom
system if for people who didn't know the
zoom system was actually originally
built by us uh between 2017 and 2023 all
the transcript you see on zoom was
generated by
>> how did it get into zoom is that like a
commercial contract or something.
>> Yeah, we we had they licensed our
technologies uh
>> and still ongoing. They're still
>> uh they they uh after they went IPO,
they didn't want to use us anymore. But
uh uh but we still have a better
technology. Uh today uh the the the
vision has evolved on this slide. We
call it the conversational knowledge
engine. Um you know when people talk
about knowledge base um
traditionally people only think about
Google document, notion doc or word doc
uh or anything uh in the CRM or my SQL.
Most people uh overlooked uh the biggest
uh source of knowledge uh is actually
came from voice. Uh for most people here
I'm sure you have tons of meetings every
day, every week. Uh if you're a manager,
if you're a leader, uh you have even
more meetings because you manage more
projects, you manage more people. Uh
you're often backto back meetings. You
know, some some of you probably spend 70
80% of your time in meetings. That's
actually where most of the business
intelligence is generated.
>> Traditionally, it's mostly lost. Um, you
know, you know, I actually just met and
interviewed and hired my first person
who has been doing all of their coding
and work by voice. He's a Princeton,
class of 2025. And it's funny because
there are all these psychology studies
that say we're by far at our happiest
when we're speaking. And but most of our
lives are in front of a keyboard and a
screen typing. And you know, it's just
the way the certy keyboard evolved.
There's nothing natural about it at all.
He actually doesn't type.
Yeah. Speaks everything which is
technologically possible. Very few. Has
anyone done that? Moved to that mo? Oh,
actually there are a couple. Yeah.
Really rare though. Uh but I think it'll
be the most common way to interact going
forward.
>> I I I think that's uh where the world is
moving. Um I I think eventually most
people don't need to type anymore. uh
today you know the when you use any
software system CRM HRS ERP uh the user
interface uh require you to type the
information into the database
>> um it's slow but if again if you think
about most of your your knowledge your
discussion your brainstorming decision
making status update almost everything
happened in meetings uh using voice
>> so our vision that you just talk you
know Otter or whatever we build you know
the conversation knowledge engine will
do everything for you so you almost
never need to type anymore does that
explain why so your slide here says 100
million ARR which is phenomenal by the
way but somewhere in here I saw some
monster TAM yeah 100 billion dollar
category so how is that defined as yeah
all
>> voice that sounds like a big number but
I think that's actually a uh under
estimation uh because if you search on
Google the people say hey the CRM uh uh
market has a hundred billion dollar uh
um uh attemp
if you think about CRM is only takes
care of sales meetings or sales uh data
um but your your your company has uh
many other teams in addition to sales
team right their engineering team their
product team, their marketing team,
their recruiter, uh finance, every every
team needs to have meetings.
>> Yeah.
>> So if you think about that, the the
total addressable market will be
actually way bigger than 100 billion. uh
walk us through, you know, CRM is a
really interesting case study because
CRM was trending toward being basically
a $50 product from Microsoft and then uh
Salesforce.com and prior to that, Sevil
Systems said, "No, we're going to make
this a $10,000 a seat uh force
multiplier for your Salesforce and we
can prove that you get more than $10,000
of increased productivity per person.
Therefore, pay us for the value." So
then here comes Otter. You could
perceive it either either way, you know,
notetaking becomes a free embedded
component in the operating system. You
know, Google gives it away. Or you could
see it as a well, this is so valuable to
my life. Completely changes my
productivity. I'm going to do all of my
future interactions with AI through
voice. This is worth hundreds of
billions of dollars. And so the value to
society is clear, but the business
model, you know, which it could go
either way, just like CRM could have
gone either way.
Um yeah the the business model will
definitely evolve. Um the most of the
SAS uh products have a seedbased
pricing. Um and you know more and more
products are exploring usage based
pricing. Um right cloud by anthropic is
making tons of money because people
using co-work and using their agents. Um
we see that's uh uh probably the model
Otter will adopt as well. Um the idea is
that hey you have you know five people
talking about uh a product idea you
brainstorm for an hour at the end of the
meeting the the product uh requirement
document is dropped it for you
automatically you don't need to type
anything other by just listening will
write the PRD for you instantly.
>> Yeah there's there's a question on that
actually. So you're calling that it says
here the conversational knowledge
engine. Do you have a slide on that
actually? Yeah, maybe just one. Um,
yeah, this is a high level architecture.
Uh, in the past again as we just uh
covered you you type everything. uh you
spend eight hour well let's say you
spend six hours meeting at the end of
the day you need still need to uh use
your uh laptop to enter everything into
uh your CRM your database write emails
write Slack messages
uh eventually we say hey you just talk
we just do everything for you if you say
during the meeting you say hey I need to
tell Simon about that okay we go ahead
and send a Slack message to Simon right
away you need to wait, you know, uh most
people will forget all all those things
after the meeting because they have
another meeting coming up. So, we're
building this big blue box which we call
uh conversational knowledge engine. It
does several things. It capture as much
as possible. Um but if you think about
it actually even though meeting noteaker
getting more popular majority of the
meeting are still not captured. And the
second thing is for us to use AI to
understand the content. Uh building a
knowledge graph uh with entities like
people. People are the most important
entities. Um the projects um customers
uh really and then create the
connections between everyone.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh between the PM, engineer, designer,
the sales, marketing uh who um who needs
to collaborate with whom. And we, you
know, by listening to, you know,
hundreds, thousands of meetings, the
engine actually knows everything about
your business.
>> And then does all that data bea become a
competitive moat and you hold on to it
or is the data instantaneously portable
to 100 other platforms?
>> Um well the the data obviously is owned
by the customer themsel. Uh we
definitely we create this platform for
them to uh create the uh a knowledge uh
graph and knowledge engine. Um the
reason we use the word engine is to take
action. You know once you build this
knowledge graph you can enable two
things. Once you enable every human
being to be more productive you give
them insights. Um you share uh
information with them even for uh from
meetings you didn't go to. You're
working on some project, someone else in
the engineering team, they change
something and the knowledge graph knows
that your work depend on your their uh
their their work. When they change
something,
>> even though nobody remembers to tell
you, the AI knows you should know and it
can notify you so that um you know it
fix the information silo problem.
>> That to me is the perfect segue into
what I think is the most interesting
question of all. So, I'm going to skip
ahead to it because it it's I just can't
resist. Um, so here's the question.
Capturing the knowledge is basically a
cooked solve problem, but putting it to
work goes to basically infinity. There's
no end to the ways you could use that
knowledge.
So,
you're you're shipping a meeting
participants now. Then real decisions
happen after the fact with human teams,
but that's going to move to AI based
decisions at some rate. So then the
question is well why were we meeting in
the first place like what was the
purpose of us talking to each other
which is kind of a scary thought if you
take
>> eventually eventually maybe you don't
need to meet anymore because AI will do
everything but um I I guess it will
still take some years I don't know it's
5 years 10 years
>> um people as I mentioned you probably
don't need to type anymore um but uh
people will keep talking
>> um even not for work even for you know
for fun, you still talk.
>> Well, if if we're talking for fun
though, are we going to run it through
Otter and take notes?
>> Um, that's that's arguable. I I my view
is that yes, uh because um Otter can
help you with your life as well. Um when
you argue with your wife, maybe Otter
can come and uh and uh help resolve
mediate. Uh
>> I never said that. Well, it's right here
in Otter. I don't know what to say.
>> So, when when people get married, they
they should use Otter to capture all the
promises. Oh, okay. Every wedding. Okay.
[laughter]
>> You built into the ring.
>> Yeah. Eventually I I will review how
many promises did you fulfill.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> Uh I love the way everybody at this
conference says well that's like five or
10 years in the future. Like remember
the old days that was not very far away.
Now five or 10 years is like oh you know
that'll be post AGI who cares.
Yeah, there there's another aspect
actually you know people would never
stop talking right people start uh have
been talking for I don't know hundreds
of thousands of years before uh the
written language was even uh invented
right um and the keyboard was it it's a
recent invention as well
>> there's actually a raging debate at MIT
right now about what LLM AI or you know
transformer AI really is uh you just
massive amounts of training data uh and
it interpolates and it knows so much and
it seems brilliant but is it just
interpolating and not having net new
brilliant insights or is it an illusion
that it's having brilliant new insights
and because there's a version of the
world where 5 years from today AI is
massively [clears throat] productive but
it's five or seven people in a meeting
room painting the vision for the future
and then deploying AI to achieve it and
then there's a vision five or 10 years
in the future where AI had the idea and
what why would we even have this
And the most of MIT is in camp A. I
think a lot of Stanford actually is in
camp B. Uh but I don't think anyone
really is predicting it particularly
well. So the use case for Otter in camp
A is like just goes to to the moon. It
goes to infinity.
>> There there's a infinite amount of uh um
use cases. Uh you you said okay maybe
seven people are meeting in the one
meeting room. in the past that uh most
of that knowledge is actually never
shared uh outside of that that room.
>> Um even though it's probably useful by
maybe another hundred people just just
nobody has access to it. Yeah.
>> So we we we're solving that problem
first. Um secondly as I said it it's
like you know between your sales
marketing customers you know for us uh
inside our small team um we actually
share all the customer sales calls with
everyone in the company. So everyone can
listen to the customers firsthand. So
engineers can hear what the customers
are complaining about what bugs they
complain about. The PM can hear about
that. So, so it it this shared memory is
super important for enterprises to be
productive.
>> Have you noticed how [clears throat]
like I'm recording the Moonshots podcast
twice a week and I was very very
cautious the first couple times I was on
camera and now I'm just dropping fbombs
all over the place and yeah, the
production team will probably take that
out. Who cares? But it hasn't come back
to bite me in the ass yet. But [snorts]
have you noticed people actually
changing their behavior when everything
is constantly recorded and you know that
if you say something toxic it's recorded
every time. Um it it does change
people's behavior. Uh but eventually
people will take it for granted. Uh
eventually people will assume everything
they said will be captured. Although you
know for enterprises there are always
exceptions. There are 101 ones. There's
HR uh legal financial issues. you don't
want to capture it or even if you
capture you have strict strict access
control. So all those are built into the
system
>> to control the access lock the access
but also of course I mean if you say
something bad accidentally you know we
there we're building a mode to uh redact
certain things for you
>> can you trust it?
>> Um
it should be pretty pretty pretty good.
Uh we're still working on that. You know
there the critical things you don't want
to leave a record. You say hey that's
off the record. You know maybe we go
ahead and just remove that instantly.
>> I left us a couple minutes for the fun
questions from the crowd. So I got to
pull them up here. But you can say
something brilliant and while I while I
find it here.
>> Uh you have any slides you didn't
>> Yeah, you can. You can ask people to
ask.
>> All right. I really wanted to do
question eight. Uh where is that?
All right. If Otter This is from the
crowd. But I didn't make it up. If Otter
could summarize my love life based
purely on my meetings, should I be
impressed or deeply concerned?
[laughter]
[clears throat]
>> Um, I guess that's a really debateful um
[laughter]
um it it I I uh I think it's probably a
good thing the because the um you know
even myself uh I don't think I'm a good
listener. uh if if AI can help me listen
better. Uh actually I use that all the
time now. After a meeting with the
customer, I I actually asked AI to grade
myself. How did I do? Did I did I ask
questions the the right questions?
>> Did I pick up the cues uh that the
customer implied
>> uh or did I talk too much? I think you
know that the same principle can be
applied to uh your personal life as
well. Yeah, that that capability must
not have existed or even been close when
you started the company. Now the
sentiment analysis is unbelievable.
>> Yeah. Um eventually, you know, I I had
this fantasy that hey um eventually my
whole life is captured by AI, right? Um
you know, I'm I'm already doing that. I
have I have two watches. I wearing two
watches because I run marathons. I have
a lot of uh lot of metrics capture.
>> Yeah. Uh so that's just my um uh health
metrics but you know my emotional my uh
my intellectual uh data you know it's
usually uh manifested by voice.
>> Yeah. So I like I love to have AI
capture almost everything. Um and
eventually this is your personal coach.
This is your um your your uh personal uh
assistant as well. You know again but
these are all personal use cases but you
know for us you know we're really
focusing on the team use case now.
>> Are there any metag glasses people out
there recording right now?
>> Shockingly no. Right here in in the
heart of Silicon Valley nobody's Yeah.
That's that's an interesting debate,
too, because there's, you know, glasses,
there's a pendant, there's a just always
on video and audio recording that's
coming imminently, but a lot of people
seem to be avoiding it. You don't want
to be that person, I guess. So, I don't
know what you see and don't see in the
transcripts from all the customers, but
the question is, what's the most
outrageous thing that Otter has ever
just transcribed in a meeting?
>> You could probably just AI query that up
on the fly if you want.
>> Um, I don't know. We we we cannot we
cannot see customers meetings.
Obviously, it's uh it's all uh
encrypted. Um I I'm sure I'm sure
there's
>> Here's here's one that I actually is a
function I really need. I don't know if
you'll build it or not, but how close
are we to Otter not only transcribing
the meeting, but actually telling the
CEO when they're wrong, which is a
broader way of saying a lot of people do
have trouble with confrontation, but you
know, sometimes it's obvious that
something needs to be done or cleaned up
or changed and everybody knows it, but
nobody's willing to say it. Yeah, feels
like there might be a difference.
>> Yeah, this is actually where AI can be
um can have an advantage because if if
you tell the CEO they're wrong, they're
offended. But if AI tell them then, you
know, they they're probably okay. Uh
because you know what what do you do
with AI,
right? You cannot fire them or anything.
>> Yeah, exactly. There's no push back at
all. I guess you shut it off. Uh, what
what industry has the worst meeting
discipline and therefore is the best
Otter customer?
>> You must be in in pretty much every
industry, right? With $100 million ARR.
>> Yeah, we we have a lot of software
companies as our uh customers. Uh
financial is another big uh big
vertical. Surprisingly, um we're we're
getting really strong adoption by
financial companies um because they they
they are usually the slowest uh adopting
new AI technologies, but uh because of
their very super sensitive about
security, confidentiality, encryption
and everything. Um but surprisingly,
they're they they're adopting um a
technology like
>> Oh, that's interesting. Well, they they
are very slow to adopt technology, but
they also have to record everything for
regulatory reasons.
>> For regular Yeah. either regulatory or
um you know for training purposes, you
know, they they they have a lot of
meetings with their customers. They
actually one of our customers told us
they um whenever they hire a new
associate, it takes them like almost a
year to train that associate. Talking to
customers, it's a asset manager uh
management company. Um, now they're
using Otter to help with that process.
>> I don't know if anyone's ever How many
people have tried that? It's so fun. You
You basically simulate a conversation.
It's usually a sales conversation. It
could be, but it could be a dating
conversation. Wouldn't matter. And in
real time, you have to speak and then it
scores you as you're going. At first,
it's very disconcerting, but after
you're into it, then it's Yeah, you're
you it's you know, it's like having a
like if you imagine kids playing soccer,
they're all over the map. like they're
all just like running in random
directions and if you had a personal
coach in everybody's AirPods telling
them no no no what you want to do now is
go left the team would be incredible but
there aren't enough coaches but AI can
see and coach everybody so then you
translate that over to sales behavior
and you're like every sentence you say
is scored
>> for financial companies because
everything they say uh is has a a big
stake you know they you may gain
>> or maybe illegal you know gain win or
lose a million dollars. So everything is
super critical. So yeah, you just
mentioned uh coaching. So we we actually
uh we we build a live coaching system.
Uh whenever when when you have a live
zoom call or Google meet call with the
customer um actually the the AI actually
giving you listen in real time and give
you live live uh advice and if the
customer ask certain question you cannot
answer the AI give you the answer right
away. You basically just read the answer
back.
>> It's actually one of my absolute
favorite AI use cases because I think we
all live relatively unoptimized lives.
You know, maybe as little as 5 or 10%
utilized lives because all of the
options are overwhelming and the person
you could turn to and talk to right now,
we've got you've got over 150 choices.
You know, what's the optimal choice?
It's very hard to know. And so all of
life is full of these little forks in
the road. And if you look at the success
of Silicon Valley compared to pretty
much any other city in the country, it
shows you how random those bumping. Like
the density of good bumpins here is so
much higher. And that creates massive
amounts of concentration of success, but
somebody in Atlanta, not to pick on
Atlanta right now, could find the one
other person in Atlanta that knows Sam
Alman or whatever, and then but you just
don't have the AI helping you with every
little step along the way yet. But when
you do, I think we're going to have much
more optimized lives.
>> Yeah. I I see, you know, the a um a
conversational knowledge engine like
this can really help connect people. It
connect all the meetings, connect all
the people, share the knowledge and you
know,
>> so final question, you may have already
answered it just now, but if you could
invent one feature that would instantly
make every meeting 10 times better, what
would it be? And can it phase
>> make people show? Can Oh, can a phase
make people shut up? Yeah. Okay. Ignore
that.
>> Yeah. The the Well, um I I don't think
it's one feature, but eventually you
say, "Hey, you you you spend an hour and
talk about all the action items you need
to do." By the end of the meeting, AI
say, "Hey, I have finished all of them."
>> Yeah, I love that. I love that. Sam,
this has been fantastic. Thank you very
much. Appreciate the uh taking the time.
>> Thank you. Yeah. [applause]